

ING.DR. SAMBA SESAY

PROFILE

A dynamic professional engineer with over eighteen years of experience in the field of Telecommunication, Electrical and Electronic Engineering. Committed to making a significant impact in these sectors as they become pivotal in national development and globalization.

CONTACT



+232-76323708



sambasey@gmail.com, samba.sesay@usl.edu.sl



3 Turay Drive, Korgbol, Ogoo Farm, Freetown

REFERENCE

Name: Prof. Jonas A.S Redwood-Sawyerr

Position: Professor, Electrical & Electronic Engineering Department Fourah Bay College, University of Sierra Leone

Address: 5, Macfoy Lane, Congo Town,

Freetown, Sierra Leone **Email:** abiosehrs@gmail.com

Tel: +232-76670904,

EDUCATION

PhD in Communication and Information System Engineering

Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan, China September 2003 – June 2006

M.Eng in Telecommunication and Electronic System Engineering

Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan, China September 2000 – June 2003

B.Eng (Hons) in Electrical and Electronics Engineering

Fourah Bay College, University of Sierra Leone **July 1998**

Higher Teachers Certificate SLHTC(s)

Milton Margai Teachers College September 1987 – July 1990

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

Head of Department and Senior Lecturer

Electrical & Electronic Engineering Department, Fourah Bay College, University of Sierra Leone

January 2015 - Present

- General administration of the department
- Superintends the running courses and researches
- Lectures Digital System Design, Satellite Communication and Electronics.

Ag. Technical Director/Network Quality Manager

Comium SL. Ltd.

2009 - 2014

- Provides leadership and direction for the Technical Units
- Develop Network Stability and Quality Improvement Strategies
- Prepare Network Expansion and Modernization plan
- Produce Monthly and annual technical reports
- Conduct Performance appraisal and represent the company in all external technical issues.

UMTS Product Manager

Huawei Technologies Co. Ltd. Shenzhen China.

June 2006 - February 2009

- Design of mobile networks
- Technical presentations and training
- Participation in Telecommunication bidding projects in 21 countries

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

- Council Member, Sierra Leone Institution of Engineers
- Programme Development and Implementation Manager, National Science, Technology, and Innovation Council.
- Board Member, Independent Media
 Commission IMC
- Sierra Leone Team Lead, African Satellite Constellation AFCONSAT
- Member, Sierra Leone Open Data Council
- Member, National Technical Committee of the Sierra Leone Standards Bureau
- Member ECOWAS Technical Harmonization Committee THC5

SPECIAL SKILLS

- Communication Networks design
- Network Quality Analysis and Control
- Digital Transformation
- Energy modeling systems
- Renewable energy solutions design and implementation
- Project Management

LANGUAGE

- English
- Chinese (Madarin)

PUBLICATIONS

- 1.F. Gardumi, L. Petrarulo, S. Sesay, "Supporting a self-sustained energy planning ecosystem: Lessons from Sierra Leone," Energy for Sustainable Development, Vol 70, Oct. 2022.
- 2.S. Sesay, Z. Yang, J. He, "A Survey on Mobile Ad hoc Wireless Network," Information Technology Journal, Vol 3, No. 2, 2004.
- 3.S. Sesay, Z. Yang, B. Qi, J. He, "Simulation Comparison of Four Wireless Ad hoc Routing Protocols," Information Technology Journal, Vol 3, No. 3, 2004.
- 4.S. Sesay, J. He, C. Qing, Z. Fan, "A Beam Broadcasting Protocol for Ad hoc Wireless Network," 计算机科学, 2005.
- 5. J. Xiang, S. Sesay, Y. Wang, J. He, "Ad hoc Network State Aware Routing Protocol," IEEE WCNC 2007, Hongkong, China, 2007.
- 6.S. Sesay, J. Xiang, J. He, Z. Yang, W. Cheng, "Hotspot Mitigation in Mobile Ad hoc Networks," ITST 2006, Chengdu, China.
- 7.Z. Yang, S. Sesay, Z. Fan, J. He, "Gradient Broadcasting in Mobile Ad hoc Wireless Network Using Smart Antenna," Asian Journal of Information Technology, Vol 3, No.10, 2004.
- 8.S. Sesay, Z. Yang, J. He, C. Qing, "Joint Load Balancing and Hotspot Mitigation over MANET," WirelessCom 2005, Maui, Hawaii, USA.
- 9.S. Sesay, J. Xiang, J. He, X. Du, "Ensuring Efficiency and Robustness in MANET," Mobility 2005, Guangzhou, China.
- 10.Z. Yang, S. Sesay, C. Qing, D. Xu, "Securing Sensitive Data in Databases," American Journal of Applied Sciences, Vol 1, 2004.
- 11.S. Sesay, Z. Yang, C. Qing, D. Xu, "A Secure Database Encryption Scheme," IEEE CCNC'05, Las Vegas, Nevada, USA.
- 12.J. Xiang, J. He, S. Sesay, N. Xie, "Subjective Quality Evaluation for Voice Over MANET," WirelessCom 2005.
- 13. N. Xie, J. Xiang, J. He, S. Sesay, "A Packet Loss Salvation Scheme for Voice over MANET," IEE Mobility Conference 2005.
- 14.S. Xu, Z. Yang, Y. Tan, W. Liu, S. Sesay, "An Efficient Batch Rekeying Scheme," ISCIT 2005, Beijing China.
- 15.S. Xu, W. Chen, Y. Tan, S. Sesay, W. Liu, "Fast Rekeying of Multimedia Dimensional Hierarchical Tree," ISCIT 2005, Beijing China.
- 16. L. M. and S. Sesay, "Performance Degradation of Radio Channels near Residential Areas," IEEE MAPE 2005, Beijing China.
- 17. L. M. and S. Sesay, "Mobile Base Station Transmitters Installations Arouse Human Health Concerns," World Engineers' Convention, Shanghai, China, 2004.